Guide to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Complaints of Discrimination during World War II ALBA.069
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Complaints of Discrimination during World War II
1941-1946
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
ALBA.069
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
During World War II nearly 500 Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans enlisted in the U.S. armed forces. Many served with distinction, were decorated and were cited for heroism. Some found, however, that their time in Spain battling Franco’s insurgent forces seemed to compromise their status in the U.S. military. This collection consists of World War II letters from more than 70 volunteers to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade headquarters in New York City, some of them documenting discrimination against Lincoln Brigade veterans by the U.S. military. Also included are files of letters from Jack Bjoze, the Executive Secretary of VALB, to U.S. military officials, government officials, and newspaper columnists seeking to expose and end an apparent policy that prohibited some veterans from promotion or from participating in active service; and files documenting cases that VALB regarded as the main instances of discrimination.
Provenance
The collection Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Complaints of Discrimination during World War II came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
During World War II, still smarting from the fascist conquest of the Spanish Republic and determined to defeat the Axis powers, nearly 500 Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans enlisted in the U.S. Armed Forces. Many served with distinction, were decorated and were cited for heroism. Some found, however, that their time in Spain battling Franco’s insurgent forces seemed to compromise their status in the U.S. military. Early in 1943, staffers at the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) headquarters began receiving reports of incidents of discrimination against Lincoln Brigade veterans serving in the Army. Some Brigade veterans claimed that they had been denied commissions and active overseas duties, others found themselves transferred to limited-service units along with pro-fascists and Nazi sympathizers.
VALB Executive Secretary Jack Bjoze launched a vigorous campaign to end an apparent policy that prevented some veterans from participating fully in active service. He sent formal protests to military and government officials and, lobbying support on behalf of the sidelined veterans, made these alleged abuses known to the public. “These men were among the first Americans to fight Hitler and Mussolini,” asserted Bjoze in a January 1943 article published in PM, “and all they want is a chance to continue their fight against Fascism.” By the end of April, Congressman John M. Coffee petitioned the Secretary of War, Robert Patterson to conduct an investigation of the allegations leveled by Bjoze. Despite repeated appeals, Army officials denied the existence of any formal policy barring members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade from combat duty or advancement. However, following columnist Drew Pearson’s exposé of the military’s unjust treatment of Spanish Civil War veterans, many Brigade veterans who had struggled to overcome the obstacles that deprived them of combat postings, were at last deployed to active service. In an October 1943 letter to Pearson, Bjoze expressed his gratitude:
"Pertaining to the …boys the condition is greatly improved. We sincerely appreciate your efforts in their behalf, as we feel that it was one of the primary causes responsible for the War Department lifting the ban, to a large extent, on sending the boys overseas."
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Letters From Veterans. This series consists of World War II letters written by Lincoln Brigade veterans to staffers at the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) headquarters in New York City documenting discrimination against them by the U.S. military. Included are letters from the following individuals: William Aalto, Gerald Cook, Milton Felsen, Harry Fisher, Irving Fajans, Benjamin Gardner, John Gates, Michael Jimenez, George Watt and Milton Wolff.
Series II: Letters from Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) Officials. This series contains letters from VALB officials, most of them from Executive Secretary Jack Bjoze, to U.S. military officials, government officials, and newspaper columnists protesting discrimination by the armed forces against former Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteers serving in the military. The letters to officials ask for remediation of the situation; those to columnists seek public exposure. Replies to the VALB’s letters are included. This series includes notable correspondence with Drew Pearson, radical journalist George Seldes, Congressman John M. Coffee, and the U.S. War Department, as well as a letter of support from then Secretary of the Interior, Harold L. Ickes.
Series III: Case Files. This series of individual case files documents what VALB considered to be the main instances of discrimination, most of which consisted of denying volunteers assignment to combat positions and overseas service. The one exception is a file on Herman Bottcher that enumerates numerous acts of heroism on behalf of the Allied forces by this much-decorated Abraham Lincoln Brigade veteran.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into three series:
Missing Title
I, Letters From Veterans
II, Letters from Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) Officials
III, Case Files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Watt Papers, ALBA #193
Harry Fisher: World War II Letters, ALBA #221.
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
James Bernard Rucker Papers, ALBA #212
Archie Brown Papers, ALBA #207.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; World War, 1939-1945.; Articles.; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.; Aalto, William.; United States. Army; Seldes, George, 1890-1995; Watt, George, 1913-1994; Wolff, Milton.; Felsen, Milt, 1912-2005; Fajans, Irving; Gardner, Benjamin, 1907-1944; Fisher, Harry, 1911-2003; Bottcher, Herman.; Bjoze, Jack; Cook, Gerald.; Coffee, John M.; Jimenez, Michael.; Gates, John, 1913-; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Letters From Veterans
  - Aalto, William, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, Frank, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Altman, David Robert, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amery, Alfred Leopold, May 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andersen, George, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Auerbach, Louis, Apr 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baker, John E., 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Balagurchik, Ilya, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bartl, Arthur, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Begelman, Elias [Beal, Eli], 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bell, Raymond Everett, Jan 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berkowitz, Norman, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Birnbaum, Saul Israel, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bjoze, Jack, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blum, Harry, Oct 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bortz, Louis, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Borysko, Andrew, Mar 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Boxer, Jack, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brandt, Joseph, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brier, Morris [Brier, Moshe], 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Briggs, Judson Reynolds, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brostoff, Barney, Nov 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Burns, Paul A., Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Callion, Walter P., 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cane, Lawrence [Cohen, Lawrence], 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Carl, Edward, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Carroll, George R., May 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Casa-Barro, Jesus de la, Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chaiken, George, Mar 1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cobert, Joseph, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Colow, Maury, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cook, Gerald, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cooper, Jack [Levitt, Isadore], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cullinen, George Ambrose, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Curtis, Ruth [wife of Sidney Kurtz], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - De Maio, Anthony, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Demas, James J., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Demas, Nicholas J., 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Deutsch, Julius, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Drill, Joseph, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Ehrlich, Rubin, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Eider, Louis A., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Fajans, Irving, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Feller, Milton [Mike], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Felsen, Milton, Dec 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Findley, Benjamin F., May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Finkenberg, Harry, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Fisher, Harry, Oct 1943 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Fitzgerald, Daniel, 1941-1944, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Flaherty, Edward G., 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Forester, Clarence, Sep 1943 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Frait, William, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Gandell, William, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Gardner, Ben, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Garland, Walter, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Gates, John [Ragenstrich, Israel], 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Gebin, Samuel, Feb 1942 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Gianfortoni, John, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Gibbons, Joseph, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Gibons, Sam, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Gittelson, Lester L., Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gnepp, Louis, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Goff, Irving, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Goldstein, Milton, Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Golomb, Ned, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Golub, Fanny, Mar 1944 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Gordon, David, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Gordon, Lou, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Groden, Daniel, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Grodzki, Frank, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Gross, Nathan, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Grumet, Leopold, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Haas, Sol, Oct 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hakam, Harry, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Harris, Arthur, Oct 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Harris, Sydney, Oct 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hecht, Joseph, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Heinricher, Stanley Anthony, Mar 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hoff, Harold Smith, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hollander, Herman, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Holzman, Benjamin, 1938, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Horan, Edward M, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hoshooley, Jack, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hovan, John George, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Howard, Joseph, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hyman, Irving, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Iceland, Benjamin, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ilich, Ljubomir, Dec 1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Jackson, Burt E., 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Jackson, John, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Jimenez, Michael, Jan 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Johnson, Al, Nov 1943 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kall, Edwin L., 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kaufman, Rubin O., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kaye, Conrad, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Keller, Fred D., 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Kenney, Richard, Sep 1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Keossian, Armand [Kerin, Arnold], 1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Kirschbaum, Max, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Kirsh, William [Mirin, William], Apr 1942 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Koblich, John, Jun 1943 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kohn, Albert, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Konove, Milton, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Kornblatt, Sidney, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Kornblum, Morris, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Koslan, Ernest [poem on Abraham Osheroff], Dec 1943 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Koslow, Al, Jan 1943 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Kurtz, Sidney, Jan 1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Land, Sanford K., 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lanser, Manny, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lending, Edward, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Levine, Benjamin, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Levine, Louis S. [Steve], 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Levine, May, Aug 1944 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Levine, Sidney, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Lister, Frank, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Litsas, Christos E., 6-Jun-44 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lloyd, Thomas, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lockett, John A., 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Lonsky, Abraham, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Lopez, Herman, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Lossowsky, Vincent, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Love, Vaughn, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Lucid, Jack M., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Luftig, Joseph, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Lukas, Frank J., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Lustgarten, Larry, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Lytton, Alfred, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - McCarthy, Bill, May 28, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Machnich, Peter, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Maki, Martin D., 1942, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Marescie, Charles, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Markowitz, Leo, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Markowitz, Rubin, Nov 1942 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Mattson, Matthew, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Meersand, Emil, Jan 1945 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Miller James [Jack], May 1943 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Minor, Ben, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Mitchell, Irving, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Morgan, Crawford, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Morse, Eugene, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Munday, Arthur, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Nagle, Robert, Nov 1941 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Nahman, Sam, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Nobel, Henry, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Nusser, Charles, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - O'Malley, Thomas, undated-1944, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Ornitz, Louis, Feb 1943 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Osheroff, Abraham, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Page, Thomas, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Pappas, Nicholas [Mike], 1942 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Parker, Max, Oct 1944 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Parmelee, Kenneth, Aug 1944 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Payne, Perley Baldwin, Jr., May 1944 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Perrone, John, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Persoff, Jim, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Quiggle, Harlan Gerald, Jun 1944 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Rauschwald, Mark B., 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reed, Robert L., Mar 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reiter, Peter, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Richards, Frank, undated, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Robbins, Albert, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Robinson, Edward [Frenchy], Feb 1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rody, John, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rogers, Robert B., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rolfe, Edwin, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rosenstein, Herman (Gabby) [Klein, Herman], 1942, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ross, Adolph, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rossen, John, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rowlson, Lester L., Sep 1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sacal, J. D. [Sakalauskas, Joseph?], 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sands, Joseph [Joseph Anthony Santa Lucia], undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sasnoff, A., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Schmidt, James Norman, Jun 1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Schneiderman, Rubin, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Schoenberg, Harry, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Schultz, Elias, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Schwartzman, Alexander, Feb 1943 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sennett, Bill, Mar 1944 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Shafran, Jacob Joseph, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Shantzek, Michael, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Sheehan, Roy, Nov 1944 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sherod, Richard M., 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Shulman, Jack, Nov 1943 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Silverman, Conrad, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Silverman, Max, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Silverman, Samuel, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Silverstein, Arthur P., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Simonson, Sig, Feb 1943 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Slipyan, Samuel, Aug 1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Smith, Owen Jefferson, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Snyder, John William, Oct 1942 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Solic, Albert R., Oct 1942 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Steinman, Ernest T., 1942 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Stillman, Milton, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Strauss, Walter F., 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Sundsten, Tauno A., 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Sverinich, John Stephan, Nov 1942 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Takacs, Joseph P., Jun 1944 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Tamler, Boris [Budd], 1943 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Tanz, Alfred, Jan 1944 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Tayler, E. Joseph, May 1943 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Teiger, Jacob Louis, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Thayer, Donald, Aug 1944 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Thompson, Richard, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Thompson, Robert, Nov 1943 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Tisa, John, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Todorovich, Alexander, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Torey, Anthony, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Toscano, Clement B., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Treslaw, Alexander, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Viggers, Ralph, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Vogel, Joseph, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Waitzman, Samuel, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Walkoff, Leroy, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Wallach, Hy, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Wallach, Jesse, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Warren, Alvin R., 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Watt, George [Kwatt, Israel] (Missing), undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Wawrzykowski, Boleslaw, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Weinberg, Jerry, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Weissman, Irving, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Wellman, Saul, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Wesson, Neil [Weisenfeld, Nathan], 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Whalen, Joseph Albert, Oct 1943 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Wildegaus, Gustav, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Wolff, Milton, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Yates, James, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Young, Edward, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Young, Murray, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Unidentified, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Series II: Letters from Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Officials
  - Army and Navy Register, Jun 1943 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ayers, Harry M., May 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Baldwin, Joseph Clark: Congress, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Baldwin, Roger N.: American Civil Liberties Union, May 1943 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brown, Cecil: Station WABC, Apr 1943 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Celler, Emanuel: Congress, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Coffee, John M.: Congress, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Curtis, Carl T.: Congress, Oct 1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Downey, Sheridan: Senate, May 1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - DeLacy, Hugh: Congress, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Holland, Elmer J.: Congress, Nov 1942 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Ickes, Harold L.: Secretary of the Interior, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Irizana, Ernest: Japanese American Committee for Democracy, Nov 1944 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kemnitz, Milton N.: National Federation of Constitutional Liberties, Jul 1943 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Lang, John L., 1943 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Lerner, Max, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot: Senate, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Luce, Clare Boothe: Congress, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Marcantonio, Vito: Congress, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Military Affairs Committee: United States Congress, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Murray, James E.: Senate, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - New York Times, Jan 1943 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Parsons, Geoffrey, Apr 1943 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Pearson, Drew, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Pepper, Claude: Senate, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Seldes, George, [1943] (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Sinclair, Upton, Apr 1943 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - United States Army Air Force, Jan 1944 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - United States War Department, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Winchell, Walter, Apr 1943 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Wilkie, Wendell L., 1943 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Wise, James Waterman: Council against Intolerance in America, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Series III: Case Files
  - Bottcher, Herman, 1943-1944 (Box OS004, Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Brier, Morris, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Cook, Gerald, [1943] (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Fajans, Irving, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Gates, John, [1943] (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Hakam, Harry, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Hecht, Joseph, [1943] (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Jackson, Burt (also, Milton Wolff to General George Marshall), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Keller Freddy, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Nelson, Steve, Apr 1943 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Rubin, Bernard, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Watt, George, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Wolff, Milton, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Report: Summary of Discrimination Cases, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)